<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
 <title>James Johnson's Blog</title>
 <link>http://jamesjohnson.me</link>
 <description>James Johnson's Blog</description>
 <updated>2013-01-30T00:52:27-05:00</updated>
 <copyright>Copyright 2010, James Johnson</copyright>
 <language>en-us</language>
 <docs>http://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>

 
 <item>
   <title>Rails and Web Development - Take the First Step</title>
   <author>James Johnson</author>
   <pubDate>2011-10-05T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
   <link>http://jamesjohnson.me/2011/10/05/beginners-guide-to-programming.html</link>
   <guid>http://jamesjohnson.me/2011/10/05/beginners-guide-to-programming</guid>
   <description>&lt;p&gt;Getting started with web development isn&amp;#8217;t easy. Looking back to when I started, the first few weeks were the toughest to stick with it. For someone who is new to text editors and the terminal &amp;#8211; the installation process can be really overwhelming. I recently went through the process of helping some of my friends get set up with Ruby on Rails and after doing it a few times, I realized it would be helpful to write a post that others looking to get started could refer to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following is not going to fully explain the steps (which at some point will be important to understand). Instead, I tried to give explicit instructions for creating a working rails environment that hopefully will be easy for anyone with a Mac to follow. If you are interested in getting started with web dev but not sure where to begin, this is for you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) This tutorial won&amp;#8217;t work on a PC and the process is a little different for Ubuntu (which I first started on). You can buy used macbooks on eBay pretty cheap, or dualboot your PC with Ubuntu. I had someone who knew what they were doing help me with the latter when I started &amp;#8211; but I do think a Mac is the easiest option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) Install Xcode in the app store. If you have the Lion operating system installed, it&amp;#8217;s free. You can also get Lion in the app store.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src='/images/posts/learning_rails/xcode.png' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) Once Xcode is installed &amp;#8211; next step is installing homebrew. The homebrew github is &lt;a href='https://github.com/mxcl/homebrew/wiki/installation'&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; All you need to do is open your terminal from Spotlight.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src='/images/posts/learning_rails/spotlight.png' /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
and copy and paste in the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/usr/bin/ruby -e &quot;$(curl -fsSL https://raw.github.com/gist/323731)&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should look something like this:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src='/images/posts/learning_rails/terminal.png' /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From here you should see a bunch of output. If there are any points where you are asked a question, just hit enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4) After Xcode is installed &amp;#8211; its time to install git. This is really easy to do with the homebrew install. In the same way that you copy and pasted the homebrew install, you copy and paste the following line of code which will install git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew install git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again there will be a bunch of output, but there shouldn&amp;#8217;t be any issues with the install.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5) Next step is installing &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RVM&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8211; this is a ruby tool that makes managing different versions of ruby much easier. When I started this was really confusing for me, so don&amp;#8217;t worry about it too much right now. If you would like to read up on &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RVM&lt;/span&gt; (which you should!) the link is  &lt;a href='http://beginrescueend.com/'&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; To install &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RVM&lt;/span&gt; copy and paste the following (same as before) into the terminal.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;bash &amp;lt; &amp;lt;(curl -s https://raw.github.com/wayneeseguin/rvm/master/binscripts/rvm-installer)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6) This is the most complicated part of the install for a new user, you need to add &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RVM&lt;/span&gt; to your path so that you can access it everytime you use the terminal. This is done by creating or adding to an existing .bashrc file. In your terminal copy and paste the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;vim ~/.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are using a text editor that allows you to edit files. Vim has a series of commands that are great for developers but hard for a first timer to pick up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is code existing in this file, use the down arrow go to the bottom of the file and press the letter &lt;span class='light'&gt;o&lt;/span&gt;. If you make a mistake at any point. Hit the &lt;span class='light'&gt;esc&lt;/span&gt; key and press &lt;span class='light'&gt;u&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class='light'&gt;u&lt;/span&gt; will undo your changes). Once at the bottom of the file, after pressing &lt;span class='light'&gt;o&lt;/span&gt;, paste on a new line the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[[ -s $HOME/.rvm/scripts/rvm ]] &amp;amp;&amp;amp; . $HOME/.rvm/scripts/rvm&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the code is there press the &lt;span class='light'&gt;esc&lt;/span&gt; key, then type in the following &lt;span class='light'&gt;:wq&lt;/span&gt;. the &lt;span class='light'&gt;:wq&lt;/span&gt; should show up in the bottom nav of the program, you should not be typing this into the file itself. &lt;span class='light'&gt;:w&lt;/span&gt; is the command to save a file in vim and &lt;span class='light'&gt;:q&lt;/span&gt; is the command to quit, together they will save and quit. When you type &lt;span class='light'&gt;:wq&lt;/span&gt; it will save the ~/.bashrc file and exit. The image below is how it should look (ignore the colors) if you do it right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src='/images/posts/learning_rails/bashrc.png' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7) After adding &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RVM&lt;/span&gt; to the path, you will need to exit out of the terminal and reopen it. Next step is to install Ruby and then Rails! To do so, copy and paste in the following commands to the terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will install Ruby&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;rvm install ruby-1.9.2-p290&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you see the following error: &amp;#8220;rvm: command not found&amp;#8221; &amp;#8211; paste the following into the console and retry:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;source ~/.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once it is done installing you need to tell &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RVM&lt;/span&gt; that you would like to use Ruby 1.9.2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;rvm use 1.9.2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should get a green confirm message that this worked, next time to install Rails. First confirm gems are updated and then install Rails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gem update --system&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gem install rails&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8) You won&amp;#8217;t need this right away, but to use 3rd party libraries (called gems in Rails) you should install bundler now. Really helpful way to manage 3rd party software your applications will rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;gem install bundler&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9) Now create your first Rails app! &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;rails new blog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and then type in the following to &amp;#8220;change directory&amp;#8221; into your new application. Imagine that CD is the same as using a mouse to click on a directory to view its files. cd is the same concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd blog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and generate some scaffolding code, migrate the database, and start the server (this will create your first app!):&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;rails g scaffold post title:string body:text published:boolean&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;rake db:migrate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;rails s&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10) Now check out the following url to see your first rails app: &lt;a href='http://0.0.0.0:3000/posts'&gt;http://0.0.0.0:3000/posts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next steps are checking out the following guides and resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://guides.rubyonrails.org/'&gt;Rails Guide&lt;/a&gt;: Read through as much as you possibly can&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href='http://railscasts.com/'&gt;Railscasts&lt;/a&gt;: Watch the lessons and try to copy, these helped me the most as I learned&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href='http://stackoverflow.com/'&gt;Stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt;: Ask and search for questions you have here&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your first question is probably how do I edit stuff? You can use vim to open up any of the files in application you just made. For example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;vim app/views/posts/index.html.erb&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will open the index file and you can play around with changing words etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have fun and good luck!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;questions? &lt;a href='http://twitter.com/jamesjohnsona'&gt;@jamesjohnsona&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 </item>
 
 <item>
   <title>Ruby on Rails: Beginners Best Friend</title>
   <author>James Johnson</author>
   <pubDate>2011-04-23T00:00:00-04:00</pubDate>
   <link>http://jamesjohnson.me/2011/04/23/ruby-on-rails-for-beginners.html</link>
   <guid>http://jamesjohnson.me/2011/04/23/ruby-on-rails-for-beginners</guid>
   <description>&lt;p&gt;Learning to code is not easy. Like most things that are worth doing, it takes significant time, effort and suffering  to achieve a very basic level of competency. The biggest barrier I found in teaching myself was my own frustration and lack of progress. I have been doing this a little longer than a year, and it is interesting for me to look back on my progress. Early on there were some very basic problems that took weeks to figure out. It took me a while to come to terms with the fact that there was no easy way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried out a bit of php and python/django before jumping into Ruby on Rails. For someone in a position similar to me, I would highly recommend leaning Ruby on Rails if you are starting frmo scratch When I began I knew nothing, but I knew I was interested in buiding web based technology(like everyone else!). Rails made my life a &lt;i&gt;little&lt;/i&gt; bit easier for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) Scaffolding &amp;#8211; I imagine it is rarely used by those who know what they are doing, I rarely use it now and still don&amp;#8217;t know what I am doing:)- but scaffolding early on allowed me to experiment and learn code that already existed. Installing rails was pretty easy on ubuntu, and then all I had to do was run rails g scaffold Post name:string and I had a webapp! From there I had a framework in which I could learn the &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CRUD&lt;/span&gt; (Create, Read, Update, Destory) processes very quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) Convention over Configuration &amp;#8211; Looking back now, I realize I spent &lt;i&gt;very&lt;/i&gt; little time actually leaning Ruby, almost all my effort was put into learning html/css/JS/rails routes/&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;MVC&lt;/span&gt; relationships/ and  configuring gems that handled the Ruby for me. This allowed me to build a site that &lt;strong&gt;looked&lt;/strong&gt; like something I wouldn&amp;#8217;t be embarrased to show to friends. That was huge for me at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) Documentation &amp;#8211; Even now when I read python or django documentation for some projects I work on, it overwhelms me. The documentation at &lt;a href=&quot;rubyonrails.org&quot;&gt;rubyonrails.org&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;u&gt;so&lt;/u&gt; easy to follow along with. Again from someone who has no formal or informal background in development, something like this can make a huge decision when fighting against your own frustration to give up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4)Railscasts &amp;#8211; Not even sure what can be said about this. I used to be cool but now I spend Saturday nights watching them. Thank you Ryan Bates. Watching &lt;a href=&quot;http://railscasts.org&quot;&gt;Railscast&lt;/a&gt; videos are inspiring because Ryan has such a fantastic way of teaching. Every step is covered and so long as you have Ruby installed and bundler set up correctly &amp;#8211; you can have prety much no idea what you are doing and recreate most of what is covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rails is awesome, the community, the documentation, everything. The only caution I would say is that it is very easy to get caught up with the &amp;#8220;features&amp;#8221; and ignore what is really important, learning Ruby. I have spent a lot of time the past few months playing catch up geting a better understanding of the Ruby language. In order to make significant progress moving forward, this is going to need to be ongoing for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I could do it over again, I think I would learn the same way because progress early on is crucial to sticking with it. For people who have jobs, it is &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;REALLY&lt;/span&gt; hard to find the time and concentration to get started. For the first 7 months for me, my scheudle was get home at 7pm and sit at the computer until midnight, then wake up at 6:15 to go to work. It sucked at the time, so it would have been easy to quit if I wasn&amp;#8217;t seeing constant improvement. Totally worth it though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ive written (and thrown out) a lot of code in the past 6 months, but most recently working with a few friends from college, I helped build &lt;a href=&quot;http://dudedeal.com&quot;&gt;Dudedeal.com&lt;/a&gt; which is a resource for guys looking for relevant daily deals. We have the site built and currently are encouraging beta users to test it out. The deals are limited for right now, but we will be turning up the volume in the couple of weeks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/jamesjohnsona&quot;&gt;Following or @ me on Twitter if you have any questions or comments!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
 </item>
 

 </channel>
</rss>
